In the ערכין Arachin אותו ואת בנו, Oso Ve-es Beno, ע"ט, Ayin
Tes, 79, we pick up at the top of the דף, daf,
and we are in the middle of discussing the question about whether
this prohibition of slaughtering an animal, a sheep or cow and its
child, applies only to the mother and the child or even to
the father and the child, and although the verse is entirely in
the male, גמרא Gemara is predisposed to assume that it applies to
the mother because there's a clearer sense of family and of connection
between mother and child as we said sort of particularly in the
animal world because of the biological connection which lacks sort of the
same sort of social structure as human society or societal structure in
terms of the role of the father. So the family unit there
is understood to be primarily that of the mother and the child
and there's a question whether you would also include the father in
the prohibition. And this question is framed in the גמרא Gemara as
the issue about חוששין לזרע האב. choshishin le-zera ha-av. Do we concern
ourselves with the seed of the father? Now that does not mean
not to be misunderstood to mean do we know who the father
is, which you could assume is the word חוששין choshishin like,
do we know who the father is? It's taken for granted that
we're going to assume we do know, but the question is does
it really matter? And again, this is particularly in terms of the
animal world where you can understand that the father is more seen
as just the one who provides the זרע, zera, that's sort of
his whole role. He's not so much in terms of connecting to
the child, and therefore the question is does the father matter? So
this is the question in terms of אותו ואת בנו, Oso Ve-es
Beno, whether we sort of see that as a meaningful family unit,
father and child or just mother and child? And now we're going
to turn to a more general question. So we pick up on
ע"ט עמוד א', Ayin Tes Amud Aleph, and we say אמר רב
הונא, Amar Rav Huna, three lines from the top. אמר רב הונא,
Amar Rav Huna, says רב הונא, Rav Huna
fourth line now, אמר רב הונא בר חייא אמר שמואל, Amar Rav
Huna bar Chiya amar Shmuel, in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, הלכה
כחנניה. halacha k-Chananya. חנניה Chananya was the one that says that the
prohibition of אותו ואת בנו Oso Ve-es Beno applies to the father
and child as well, not just the mother and child. So the
father does have significance. ואזל שמואל לטעמיה, Ve-azal Shmuel le-tameih, שמואל Shmuel
goes according to his reasoning, and now we are going to spend
the rest of the day talking about this as a more general
question of חוששין לזרע האב choshishin le-zera ha-av and not just regarding
the prohibition of אותו ואת בנו. Oso Ve-es Beno. So let's take
a look. דתנן, Detnan, we taught in a משנה, mishna, רבי יהודה
אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, הנולד מן הסוס, ha-nolad min ha-sus, אף על
פי שאביו חמור, af al pi she-aviv chamor, מותרים זה בזה. mutarim
zeh ba-zeh. So now we're going to talk about mules, the offspring
of horses and donkeys, and presumably you can have it whether the
mother is a donkey or the father is or the mother is
a horse, it's the offspring of a horse or donkey, but it
could be either type of a crossbreeding to be you could create
a mule either having mother horse, father donkey or mother donkey, father
horse. So now the question is going to be the following: in
the prohibition of כלאים, kilayim, of crossbreeding animals, does it apply with
two mules? Do you say what's natural thing to be would be
the say, which is that mules are the regardless of who the
parents are, mules are their own species called mules, and therefore if
you crossbreed a mule with a mule, you're crossbreeding it with the
same species? Or do you say no, maybe a mule is not
is to be defined just by its mother? This would be the
principle of אין חוששין לזרע האב. ein choshishin le-zera ha-av. You ignore
the father. If you ignore the father, then a mule's real species
is what is its mother, mother species. So you could have a
mule that is essentially an offspring of a horse if the mother
was a horse, and a mule that is an offspring of a
donkey if the mother was a donkey, and you would not be
able to crossbreed the two of them, or somebody's going to say
that you can't that mules are sterile, which I know, but anyway
the attempt to crossbreed is still a problem even if you don't
produce offspring, or let's say have them draw a carriage together because
there's a prohibition of having two different
animals share a load, carry a load, draw a carriage. So you
could not have two mules with different mothers
because one is effectively a horse and the other's effectively a donkey.
So that is the question of whether you concern yourself with the
father or you don't, and do you see this as a crossbreed
or do you see this fundamentally as the child of its mother?
Yes.
It is very rare, but on rare occasions female mules have had
colts.
Female mules have had colts. So mules if mules can, it's possible
to produce offspring.
Okay. Colts you mean a horse or you mean a mule?
Well, you don't know. Okay. That's the question.
Anyway, having them mate, even without the production of offspring, is the
biblical prohibition of לא תרביע, lo tarbia, which means to not not
to produce offspring, but to actually have them cross, have them cross
mate. So that's the issue. So let's take a look. דתנן, Detnan,
we taught in the משנה, mishna, רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer,
הנולד מן הסוס. ha-nolad min ha-sus. That thank you mules that are
born from a horse. Now notice again the irony, we were pointing
about the irony yesterday that the תורה Torah speaks about אותו ואת
בנו, oto v'et beno, but the גמרא Gemara says that it is
most obviously talking about the mother. So here too we are going
to use the masculine referring to the mother. Okay. We said הנולד
מן הסוס, hanolad min hasus, but we really mean מן הסוסיה, min
hasusya, yes. What is the Hebrew for a סוסה, susa, מן הסוסה?
min hasusa? Okay? But again נולדים noladim mean the we are focusing,
the primary parent we are focusing on here is the mother although
we will throughout this דף daf refer to her sometimes in the
masculine. Just to reflect what we have done to the פסוק. pasuk.
So הנולדים מן הסוס, hanoladim min hasus, the mules that are offspring
of a of a female horse. אף על פי שאביהן חמור, af
al pi she'avihen chamor, see it is explicit, although their father is
a donkey, מותרין זה בזה. mutarin ze bazeh. So you can have
you know you can have all all mules that share the same
type of a mother, a horse mother, have interbreed and it does
not matter that they are that they are all mules because as
long as they have right, exactly, as long as they all have
a mother, a as long as their mother is a horse. אבל...
aval...
מן הסוסים? min hasusim?
No, that is a good question, we will get to that. אבל
הנולדים מן החמור עם הנולדים מן הסוס אסורין, aval hanoladim min hachamor
im hanoladim min hasus asurin, but mules whose mother are donkey cannot
crossbreed with mules whose mother is a horse because one is considered
effectively a horse and the other is considered effectively a donkey because
we ignore the father. That is the position of the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma that we ignore the father. זו ד... whatever, okay. ואמר
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda, אמר שמואל, Shmuel now רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda
that
is a משנה. Mishnah. Now רב Rav יהודה said in the name
of שמואל Shmuel because the משנה Mishnah said it in the name
of רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and there is no no dissenting opinion.
So now שמואל Shmuel said זו דברי רבי יהודה, zu divrei Rebbi
Yehuda, this is only the opinion of רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda דאמר
אין חוששין לזרע האב de'amar ein chosheshin lezera ha'av who is effectively
saying we do not concern ourselves with the father and the mule
is considered to be of the species of the mother. אבל חכמים
אומרים, aval Chachamim omrim, but there is a majority opinion not recorded
and that position is כל מיני פרדות אחת הן, kol minei peradot
achat hen,
all types of mules are the same. Mules are the parents are
considered equally the mother and the father and therefore all mules are
considered a crossbreed and therefore they are all considered their own type
of מין, min, their own species. They are not a horse, they
are not a donkey, they are a mule and therefore all different
all mules regardless of what the who the mother is are can
be crossbred. So here you see this issue of חוששין לזרע האב
chosheshin lezera ha'av applied to the question of the identity of a
crossbreed. Now I should point out, and let me actually point out
here that you know there is a big תוספות Tosafos because there
are different סוגיות sugyot in ש"ס Shas between are you חושש לזרע
האב, choshesh lezera ha'av, לא חושש לזרע האב, lo choshesh lezera ha'av,
and the conclusion is is seems to be different in different גמרות.
Gemarot. Okay, this גמרא Gemara seems to come out like the position
that we rule like חנניה Hananya חוששין לזרע האב chosheshin lezera ha'av
and it is forbidden in אותו ואת בנו, oto v'et beno, other
גמרות Gemarot come out with other conclusions. So it is worth noting
that it is that it is not necessarily the same question we
asked yesterday and we are asking today. Yesterday we were asking does
the father and child in the animal kingdom form a family unit
so that when the תורה Torah prohibits אותו ואת בנו oto v'et
beno it is reasonable to say that it is prohibiting father and
child as well. We see those as some type of a family
unit. This is not a question of family unit. This is a
question of almost genetics, right? Do we say that the offspring is
an offspring of both the father and the mother? And the answer
is yes, even if the father deposit you know sort of is
the the sperm donor and gives his seed and walks away and
is never part of the family unit, the child is still a
a crossbreed you know of the two of them, a hybrid of
the two of them. So it would be very reasonable to say
that it is not included in אותו ואת בנו oto v'et beno
because he is not part of the family unit, but the child
is still considered equal parts donkey and and and horse, right? So
they are really different questions. It is actually quite a little surprising
to say we go so far to say we discount the father
that we are going to consider this mule to really be a
horse and we are going to consider this other mule to really
just be a donkey. Okay that obviously takes it to the next
you know to another level. Okay so let us continue in the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so שמואל says we the חכמים, Chachamim, so the
majority position is that the father is a factor and all and
all mules are considered to be an equal hybrid and the and
we do weigh in the role of the father. Okay, so let
me though we are going to let me just read one more
and then you will ask your question. Okay, אחת הן, achat hen,
so מאן חכמים, man Chachamim, who are the חכמים Chachamim match up
with? חנניה הוא, Hananya hu, the חנניה Hananya that we quoted yesterday
about the prohibition of אותו ואת בנו oto v'et beno דאמר חוששין
לזרע האב de'amar chosheshin lezera ha'av
that says that we are concerned with the seed of the father,
that the father's role is significant. והאי בר סוסייא וחמרא, v'hai bar
susaya vechamra,
one of them is the offspring of a horse and a donkey,
והאי בר חמרא וסוסייא, v'hai bar chamra vesusaya, and the other one
is the offspring of a donkey and a horse, the first one
presumably... being the mother. Notice, by the way, they're the exact same
words; there's no feminine here, right? In both cases, they use the
exact same words to describe who the father, whether they were describing
the father or the mother. Anyway, that's just the Gemara again sort
of defaulting to the masculine. But nevertheless, since we weigh in the
contribution of the father, therefore all these mules are equally equal hybrids.
And therefore כולו חד מינא נינהו, kulu chad mina ninhu, they're all
the same species and you can crossbreed them because they are all
equal hybrids. Okay, so again, this is taking, this is of course,
you would never have thought, I think, if we
hadn't said yesterday, I don't think would have made you sort of
expect what we were going to see today. It's one thing to
say we discount the father as part of the family unit, he's
not prohibited in אותו ואת בנו. oto v'et b'no. It's quite another
thing to say that that means that a mule is really just
considered a horse because we completely ignore even his genetic contribution. Okay,
so obviously, but the Gemara says there is some way that they
line up, but again the point I'm making is also that תוספות
Tosafot and other ראשונים Rishonim say the סוגיות sugyot are not always
consistent how we rule. So it's worth noting that the questions are
not always the same question. Michael, you had a question.
Yeah, I was more of just a comment. That the way they
frame this here is חכמים או חנניה Chachamim o Chananya and he
says חוששין לזרע אבא, chosh'shin l'zera aba, but the way it was
introduced yesterday, it's really not חוששין לזרע אבא chosh'shin l'zera aba question
as much as how you interpret the פסוקים, pesukim, you know what
I mean? But this, they just straight אותו, oto, he says, I
mean if I remember correctly, he says אותו oto is משמע זכר
mashma zakhar and then he says בנו b'no כרוך אחריו, karukh acharav,
which is sort of like how you...
Yes, but as the Gemara said, and that actually- this is actually
quite important because it gets into the question about how often do
we think that differences in הלכה halakha and interpreting the פסוקים pesukim
are purely mechanical questions about what do you do with this extra
ו vav or how much or whatever, do you דרשן darshen this
extra word or not, or how much are those interpretive questions questions
also about
what issues are informing
your assumptions and why you might want to see it have this
sort of parameters versus those parameters. And the Gemara yesterday was actually
quite interesting in that regard. It basically said if your basic position
is that you don't see the father as relevant, even though the
verse is written in the masculine and the verse should incline you
to assume we're including the father, a general sense that fathers in
the animal kingdom don't matter is going to push you the other
way. Whereas opposed to if you generally think that fathers in the
animal kingdom do matter, then you're going to interpret the verse כפשוטו.
kipshuto. So the Gemara actually was very significant in that regard. It
said it's not always, when you have debates of interpretation, what informs
why one person reads the extra word this way and the other
that way? Sometimes other assumptions inform it and the Gemara was quite
clear about that.
The other thing I was going to say was, which I find
this kind of ironic that are we worrying about the father but,
with horses specifically we're very, very concerned with the father. Like studs
and all that. I understand. And these things go for millions of
dollars to have like a progeny...
I understand.
So if the question is, are we- do we still- yes, you
have stud farms and whatever, but do we consider them any more
than just sperm donors? That's the question. So that's a great question.
Are they really part of the family? And that's a question of
אותו ואת בנו. oto v'et b'no. So but there- but yes, it
is a
little bit- a jump, not just a little jump, to say that
we completely discount them even in terms of the genetic makeup of
the child, which is what our Gemara is doing. Yes, David, you
had a question.
Are there offspring, which
is
the mother and which is the father? Do we have two different
species coming out of this or one species?
No, one. The whole assumption the Gemara says there is- you're right,
in theory you could have said, yes, the father- we weigh in
the father, but we still see that a hybrid that,
when the contributors are in this direction is one, and a hybrid
when the contributors are in that direction is another. But no, it
doesn't say that. In the end of the day, if they're equal
contributors and therefore these are considered all hybrids and all the same.
And are these hybrids then able to also participate in the species
of donkey and horse?
No, so that would exactly be the point and that's the Gemara
is going to get to. So according to חנניה, Chananya, you can't
crossbreed or cross-plow with a mule with a mule and a horse,
right? Because these are a hybrid species and these are a pure
species and they're different species. The question is going to be according
to the חכמים- Chachamim according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says
you only look at the mother, so can you take a mule
whose mother is a horse and crossbreed it with a horse? And
can- or have it bear a load with a horse? Is it
really fully a horse? That's going to be the next question the
Gemara is going to ask. Two more quick questions and then we're
going to continue.
Yeah, what's the source for the idea that I've read that if
two animals can mate and produce fertile offspring that they are the
same species הלכתית? halakhit?
That is based on a גמרא Gemara a little bit- on a
גמרא Gemara we had before when it was trying to figure out
kosher and non-kosher animals and birds and whatever, and it spoke about
living together and so on, and there's also a question about- the
גמרא Gemara there didn't mention it, but the question that always get
raised and comes up also
in...
Right. But anyway, but yeah, but it's not the only factor.
Okay, but
yeah, the other thing I was going to point out is that
the אותו ואת בנו Oto v'Es Beno category, that set of animals
that's relevant for, is an entirely distinct set of animals from the
כלאיים Kilayim category. I mean, I can't say, maybe I'm missing something,
but what כשר kosher animals are relevant to כלאיים Kilayim and therefore
also relevant to שחיטה shechita אותו ואת בנו? Oto v'Es Beno?
Well, you can't plow with a... You can't try to crossbreed a
cow and a sheep. And if you bizarrely tried to plow with
a cow and a sheep, you couldn't do that. Okay, I mean,
let's say you had a calf and a ram, they were roughly
the same size or something, you couldn't try to have them both
hitched and both your carriage.
In terms of like the incentive to do so, buy a horse
and a donkey and get a mule. What incentive?
All right, what do I care about incentive? It's הלכה. halacha. All
right, let's go on. The גמרא Gemara says like...
All right, I'm never going to do it.
Okay, fine. All right, let's look at the גמרא. Gemara. איבעיא להו,
Iba'ya lehu, so we raised the question: מי פשיט Mi pashit or
מיפשט, mipshat, מיפשט פשיטא ליה לרבי יהודה דאין חוששין לזרע האב. mipshat
peshita lei le-Rabbi Yehuda de-ein choshshin le-zera ha-av. When רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says you cannot crossbreed a mule whose mother is a horse
with a mule whose mother is a donkey, does he say that
we completely are not concerned with the father's contribution, it is completely
irrelevant? או דלמא ספוקי מספקא ליה, O dilma sipuki mesafeka lei,
or perhaps he's uncertain whether we are concerned with the father's contribution?
So למאי נפקא מינה, Le-mai nafka mina, what difference does it make?
Either way, either he definitely says that this mule is really a
horse and that mule is really a donkey and they can't crossbreed,
or he says maybe it's fully a horse and maybe it's fully
a donkey. Either way, they can't crossbreed. So what's the relevance of
this question? So the relevance is what Michael asked before: למישרי פרי
עם האם, Le-mishrei pri im ha-eim, to allow a fruit, an offspring
with, not necessarily its literal own mother, but with the species of
its mother. So you have here a mule whose mother is a
horse. Can you crossbreed this mule with a horse? Or either crossbreed
in terms of trying to produce offspring or crossbreed in terms of
trying to have them, you know, hitch them to your carriage. And
therefore, what's the question? Do you say it's definite that the father
is irrelevant and this mule is, could be a hundred percent horse
for all we care? If that's true, then you can crossbreed it
with a horse. Or do you say, no, I'm like a little
bit ambivalent, I'm not prepared to say that the father is, you
know, that the father is totally an equal partner and that this
has a full identity as a horse breed. Its primary identity really
might be that of a horse, and on the other hand, I'm
not prepared to completely discount the father. Maybe it does somewhat affect
the identity of this and therefore you sort of have to be
strict both ways. So because the father might be relevant and this
might be part donkey, therefore you can't crossbreed it with a horse.
Because the father might be irrelevant and it might be effectively completely
horse, you can't crossbreed it with a different type of a mule.
Okay, so you sort of are uncertain whether to give it a
mixed identity or just the mother's identity and you have to be
strict both ways. Okay, that is the question. Okay, yes.
So the mule that you're connecting the other mule with also had
to have a mother who's a horse?
Yes. So according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the only thing you
can crossbreed this way with is something that has the exact same
type of lineage. Another mule whose mother is a horse and father
is a donkey. Okay, because then regardless of what the role the
father is, whether they're, if it's irrelevant, it's irrelevant in both cases.
If it is relevant, then it's relevant in both cases and you
know you're safe if you do it with an exact similar type
of a mule. But you can't do it with a mule with
a different mother because maybe the father's irrelevant and you go totally
by the mother. And you can't do this mule with a horse
because maybe the father is relevant and it's not considered to be
a pure horse.
Oh, so now we have the product of two mules who had
mothers for horses? Yes. And now this animal is now prepared to
become a parent?
Yes, if that could happen with mules.
Once in a while it does happen. So, so how do we
know, how, that, do we then know that this mule also has
to be bred with a mother of a horse?
Yes, that's what we're saying.
Same thing again.
Oh, you mean the offspring? Oh, I see what you're saying. The
offspring of two mules, right. How much is the offspring of two
mules? That is a great question, which the גמרא Gemara does not
ask. According to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, right, is the offspring of
two mules, right, that was done correctly, is that considered just like
pure mule and it's irrelevant who it's crossbred with? Or is that
considered to be like, you know, still, right, whatever it is, you
know, still like, you know, part horse, part mule, and you still
have to work it with other horses of that same lineage? Right.
So that is a very good question, which the גמרא Gemara does
not ask. I will say, if you completely אין חוששין לזרע האב,
ein choshshin le-zera ha-av, then you're going to consider this to be
just, well actually that's a good question. Then you consider it to
be straight horse because you're considering these mules to be horse. horses
and you're going to consider it straight horse. If you are חושש
choshesh so I have to think about that but whether
you know mules are running around
the basic answer is I have to sort of like figure sort
of map it out but the basic answer is yes you would
have to ensure that it would also still be with mules that
are offsprings of a horse.
Now they have mules running around in the field.
How do you know?
How do you?
Yeah. Well, it's a good thing that mules are infertile so this
is really more of a hypothetical. Okay, let's keep on going. All
right. So is it clear to Rabbi Yehuda that you would discount
the father or is he just being safe and he doesn't know
whether to discount the father and the question is can the mule
mate with a horse? מאי mai so what's the halakha? So תא
שמע ta shema come and hear: Rabbi Yehuda says כל הנולדים מן
הסוס kol hanoladim min hasus all mules that are descendant of horses
אף על פי שאביהם חמור af al pi she'avihem chamor even though
their fathers are donkeys מותרים זה בזה muttarim zeh bazeh so you
can have them interbreed mules with the that all share the same
type of a father. So היכי דמי heichi dami what's the case?
אילימא דאבוה דהאי חמור ואבוה דהאי חמור ilima d'avuh d'hai chamor v'avuh
d'hai chamor צריכא למימר tzericha l'meimar
so if when he says they can crossbreed it's saying you can
take a mule who has a mother horse father donkey and breed
it with a mother horse father donkey so that's like patently obvious
of course that's going to be the same species. So אלא לאו
ela lav so it must be that he since he spelled it
out he's saying you can even go even further דאבוה דהאי סוס
ואבוה דהאי חמור d'avuh d'hai sus v'avuh d'hai chamor
that even in a case where one of them is really not
a mule what he says you can have all things that are
offsprings of horses interbreed what he means is all things that are
offsprings of horses. So you can have a mule whose mother is
a horse mate with a horse whose mother is a horse. Okay
and therefore and that seems because he's saying as long as things
have all things have mothers that are horses you can crossbreed them.
So it must be דאבוה דהאי סוס d'avuh d'hai sus one thing
is an offspring of not only a mother horse but a father
horse as well. ואבוה דהאי חמור v'avuh d'hai chamor and the other
is a mother horse and a father donkey. דקתני מותרים זה עם
זה d'katani muttarim zeh im zeh and he says that as long
as their mothers are a horses you can crossbreed them. So it
seems to be that that's what Rabbi Yehuda is saying and that
he completely and unequivocally discounts the father. אלמא מיפשט פשיטא ליה alma
miphshat pshita leh so you see it's obvious to him that the
father is irrelevant. So the Gemara says לא lo not necessarily. לעולם
דאבוה דהאי חמור ואבוה דהאי חמור l'olam d'avuh d'hai chamor v'avuh d'hai
chamor
really when he says that things with fathers are horses you can
crossbreed he means mules whose fathers are horses you could crossbreed. We're
only talking crossbreeding it with a mule and not talking about crossbreeding
it with a horse. So the Gemara says and if that's true
ודקאמרת צריכא למימר u'd'ka'amrat tzericha l'meimar and you said then what's what's
the chidush of course if this is a mule and that's a
mule and they both have similar parentage of course you can crossbreed
them. No maybe it's not so obvious. מהו דתימא אתי צד סוס
משתמש בצד חמור וצד חמור משתמש בצד סוס קא משמע לן mahu
d'teima ati tzad sus mishtamesh b'tzad chamor v'tzad chamor mishtamesh b'tzad sus
ka mashma lan
meaning maybe it would not have been so obvious that I can
acknowledge the identity of this species called donkey right since a donkey
is I'm not donkey excuse me mule since a mule is not
a natural species and only comes through crossbreeding right and it does
not itself propagate itself maybe there's no category halakhically as mule and
therefore every mule is really seen as half donkey half horse not
mule and therefore since it's seen as half donkey half horse maybe
I can't breed two mules together because then I'm really interbreeding two
animals. This animal is a quasi-horse and it's being interbred with another
animal that's a quasi-donkey now excuse me the other animal is also
a quasi-horse okay but if I only recognize the species of horse
and donkey then taking any animal that's part horse and interbreeding it
with some other animal that's part donkey even though this animal is
also part donkey and that animal is also part horse but nevertheless
that might have been considered interbred. Okay so קא משמע לן ka
mashma lan this is telling me that I am not concerned with
that. Since as long as the parentage is the same and one
has the same they both have the father that's a horse or
they both have the mother that's a horse I'm sorry they both
have the mother that's a horse or the mother that's a donkey
then even if then even if you acknowledge them as a new
species called mule there's no problem crossbreeding them. So that's why he
had to say it but that does not mean we would go
so far to say the mule could breed with a horse and
we completely discount the father. Yes Mordechai.
Just to inform the discussion apparently there is a big difference between
who the parentage is on male or female.
Base of mule.
Yeah mule is a male donkey and a female horse and produces
a relatively large animal and this is done frequently because they're very
good for work. Okay. A hinny is the term for a male
horse and a female donkey these are smaller and are not good
for work. Hinnies have significantly less chances of being fertile whereas with
mules male mules are virtually never fertile female mules have a one
in twenty-five chance.
Thank you Wikipedia right? By the way what you're telling me is
is that the the qualities of the mule follow more the mother
if I heard
you right.
If I remembered my genetics, that the X and Y chromosomes are
from different species,
right? So that you definitely would be, so if you'd breed these
two mules, yes,
and you trace it back to their roots, yeah, you definitely would
be, well I guess you'd have to look at percentages, so why
does it matter?
Yeah, X and Y chromosomes between horses and mules are
different in number.
Okay, that's interesting.
Oh man, okay. Well, let me just say, so let's continue, but
I do want to say that that possibility, by the way, that
is sort of floating here is never really explored in the גמרא,
Gemara, meaning what I'm about to say. The possibility is that, of
course, you do consider the father, but as Mordechai indicated, it's still
you could still say, yes, the father's a contributor, but it's a
different species when the mother is the mule than when the mother
is the horse. Meaning, the גמרא Gemara sees two possibilities. Either the
father's irrelevant and therefore the entire species is the mother's, so this
mule is basically a horse or this mule is a donkey, right?
Or the father is relevant and therefore they're equal contributors and therefore
all mules are the same regardless of who the father and who
the mother is. Right? There's a third possibility that isn't being explored,
which is the father is relevant but there are two species of
mules, there's mules and hinnies, based on who the mother is and
who the father is. That, interestingly, is not being explored in the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay. Interesting.
Yes, does the גמרא Gemara explain why we can have this initial
crossbreeding?
Oh, why it's allowed? Oh yeah, it's not allowed, but it's not
forbidden, but some non-Jew did it, yeah, or somebody did it and
transgressed,
or they did it in the wild, I don't know if that
ever happened, but right, and now you're not prohibited to use the
product of a crossbreed. The only time you're prohibited is with sort
of like, ironically maybe because you would think by animals it's a
bigger deal, but the time the תורה Torah prohibits the product of
it has to do with, you know, certain types of crossbreeding of
seeds. But of crossbreeding of actual animals, you're not prohibited to use
the offspring.
Yes, we mentioned this a few times in the past. I'm just
going to ask that because I was trying to just clarify for
myself: does
טעמא דקרא, Ta'ama Dikra, at least in terms of playing with these
two
animals, does טעמא דקרא Ta'ama Dikra come into play? In other words,
you know, if we're concerned that one's going to be weaker, one
stronger?
Yeah, no. That type of reasoning of like, like people have been
asking consistently through this מסכת Massechet about, you know, it doesn't seem
like we factor in צער בעלי חיים Tza'ar Ba'alei Chayim when we're
figuring the parameters of טרפה Treifah and so on. So I think
that's a good general question, but normally we can sometimes, you know,
it gets to the questions about דרשינן טעמא דקרא Darshinan Ta'ama Dikra
and so on. Actually, just I sent out a weekly email and
just this last week I wrote a whole thing about, you know,
exploring some of those parameters. But sometimes in some of the sort
of the parameters that are intrinsically gray, we can be informed by
certain types of, you know, assumptions about either the nature of the
מצוה Mitzvah or general assumptions to life. Here, does it apply, no,
like here, no, that's not. Like here, does it apply just to
mothers or even to fathers? So it's a little unclear from the
פסוק, Pasuk, although if anything the פסוק Pasuk seems to be saying
the opposite, but okay, there we have certain assumptions about the nature
of animal families. Okay, so there sometimes you can use certain assumptions
to guide you. But when the parameters are pretty clear and we're
going to say although it says don't do it, we're going to
say only don't do it under these circumstances because we know what
the reason of the מצוה Mitzvah is, that's a much bigger jump
and that's a דרשינן טעמא דקרא Darshinan Ta'ama Dikra type of a
concern. But that's a whole larger discussion, okay? I wrote an article
on it, I can refer you to. Let's keep on going. תא
שמע, Tashma, come and hear. רבי יהודה
אומר: Rabbi Yehuda Omer: פרדה שתבעה, Pirdah She-Tav'ah, you have a mule
that, a female mule that is תבעה, Tav'ah, which means demanding, which
is in heat and basically, you know, is demanding to have, to
be bred with, to be mated with an animal. אין מרביעין עליה
לא סוס ולא חמור
אלא מינה, Ein Marvi'in Aleha Lo Sus Ve-Lo Chamor Ela Minah, you
cannot mate it with a horse or a donkey, only its kind.
Now, so that seems like a very clear statement. This is רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, who was before discounting the father. ואי אמרת פשיטא
ליה, Ve-I Amrat Peshita Leh, and if it's obvious to רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that the father is irrelevant, מרביעה לה מינה דאימה, Mireiva
Lah Minah De-Imah, why can't you breed it with its own species,
meaning with what its mother was, מינה דאימה, Minah De-Imah, the species
of the mother? I'm sorry, so
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you cannot breed a mule with only
with another mule, you cannot breed it with a horse or donkey.
So the question is, why is it? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda discounted
the father, why can't you breed it with the same species of
the mother? If this mule is really a horse, breed it with
a horse. So you see that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda did not
completely discount the father. It's not clear to him that the father's
irrelevant. ואי, Ve-I, so the גמרא Gemara says דאימה, De-Imah,
so the גמרא Gemara says דלא ידעינן מינה דאימה, De-Lo Yad'inan Mina
De-Imah, no,
the case is we don't know the species of the mother. who
the mother is. Okay? And therefore, since you don't know who the
mother is, like you were asking before, you find a mule walking
around, what do you know about their parentage? So therefore you can't
say, oh, the mother was a horse, breed it with a horse.
Of course if that's true, then you can't also breed it with
another mule, because you have to know that it can only breed
it with a mule that has the same type of parentage.
Same mom? Maybe they morphed?
Who knows? So it depends who we rule like. Anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara says דלא ידעינן מינא דאימא מאי ניהו. d'lo yadinan mina
d'ima mai nihu.
We don't know what it is. The גמרא Gemara says והא אלא
מינה קתני, v'ha ella mina katni, but wait a minute, it says
you can crossbreed it with its own species. If you don't know
who the mother is, how can you breed it with another mule?
According, right? Because the only other mule you could breed it with
is a mule that has the same type of mother. So הכי
קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is how you have to read it: אין
מרביעין עליה לא מן סוס ולא מן חמור לפי שאין יודעין במינה.
ein marvi'in aleha lo min sus v'lo min chamor lefi she'ein yodin
bemina.
It doesn't mean you can breed it with another mule. What it
means is you can't mate it with any animal, not a horse,
not a donkey, not a mule, as long as you don't know
who its mother is, what its species is. So although here's the
statement by רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda that seems to be quite explicit
that you are not allowed to breed this mule with a horse,
with its mother's species, with a horse or a donkey, seems explicit
that we cannot completely discount the father, the גמרא Gemara re-reads it
to say it's a case where you don't know who the mother
and father is. And the way to read what רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda is saying is, here's a mule that needs to mate, you're
not allowed to mate it with any animal until you figure out
who the mother is. Okay, so that's how we re-read it. And
that it's possible that we do have to concern ourselves with the
father and cannot completely discount the father. What?
So if you found out the lineage, then you could mate it
with...
But as soon as you find out, ah, so that depends then,
meaning according to this answer of the גמרא, Gemara, although the simple
statement of רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda said you can, even if you
know the mother, you can't mate it with, even if the mother's
a horse you can't mate it with a horse, we've re-read it
to say if you don't know who the mother is, then you
can't mate it with any animal. But when you find out who
the mother is, then you can mate it with its own, with
a horse or with a similar type of a mule. So we're
trying again, the question is, does רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda completely discount
the father or not? Here was a statement that seemed to say
that he did not completely discount the father, but we re-read it
to say that maybe he does and maybe if you do know
who the mother is, you can mate it with the same type
of animal.
Like you said before, you probably could figure out who the mother
is.
Ah, there you go, so that's the next line of the גמרא.
Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says, so look, even without Wikipedia here
מרדכי, Mordechai, the גמרא Gemara says
ונבדוק בסימנין. v'nivdok besimanin. If you're trying to figure out who the
mother is, let's look at its characteristics and determine who the mother
is. What are the characteristics? So let's take a look. דאמר אביי,
d'amar Abaye, אביי Abaye says, אבי קולי בר חמרא, avi kalei bar
chamra, if it has a deep voice, it is the son of
a donkey. סניף קולי בר סוסייא, snif kalei bar susaya, if it
has a whinnying type of a high voice, then it's בר סוסייא,
bar susaya,
then it is the son, again this means the mother is a
horse. So it assumes that the voice follows the mother. Right? So
donkeys have a deeper braying than, you know, cows have a whinnying
or whatever, neighing or whatever. So anyway, the horse, it's interesting it
doesn't say the basic size, which would seem to be a much
more obvious thing. But anyway, it says the voice follows the mother.
דאמר רב פפא, d'amar Rav Pappa, and רב פפא Rav Pappa says
here are some other physical characteristics: רברבין אודני וזוטרא גנובתיה, ravarvin udnei
v'zutra gnuvatei, if it has big ears and a short tail,
so what animal has big ears and a short tail? A donkey.
So then בר חמרא, bar chamra, its mother's a donkey. זוטרין אודני
ורבה גנובתיה, zutrin udnei v'raba gnuvatei, small ears and a long tail,
then בר סוסייא, bar susaya, its mother's a horse.
Okay,
so interesting again, because they're available to even look at and observe.
Yeah,
you would think that if it were such a difference that Wikipedia
is saying, you would have also mentioned the size issue.
Maybe it's when they're little.
And maybe. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara is saying how could you
say this ברייתא braita is talking about a case where you don't
know who the mother is? You can just based, and this answers
the question, how can anybody have a
הלכה halacha that the crossbreeding depends on the mother, how do you
know what the mother is? So now they're saying, well we actually
have ways of telling. So how can you say the ברייתא braita
doesn't know who the mother is? Just look at these character traits.
So the גמרא's Gemara answer is, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan,
what are we talking about? באילמת וגידמת, b'ilemet v'gidemet,
which is a mule that is mute and that has its ears
and tail cut off. And therefore you cannot look at any of
the character traits to figure it out. So you see, it presumably
does not assume size by itself, or maybe it is young. Anyway,
so that is a pretty, that's going out on a pretty big
limb. But so it is a, the simple sense of the ברייתא
braita is that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda does not completely discount the
father, and he said you cannot breed it with a horse. But
nevertheless, we have not concluded. מאי הוי עלה, mai havi alah, what
was the upshot of this question of whether רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
completely discounts the father or not?
And you don't know what he holds either.
Right, right. תא שמע, ta shema, דאמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע,
d'amar Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua, so רב הונא Rav Huna, the
son of רב יהושע Rav Yehoshua said, הכל מודים בפרי עם האם
שאסור, hakol modim b'pri im ha'em she'asur, that at least according to
רב הונא, Huna, he said that all, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and
the חכמים, Chachamim, all agree
that you cannot
breed... So even Rebbi Yehuda that says that we discount the father,
either he's uncertain whether we completely discount him or another way to
say it is that even if he's discounted, he's largely discounted but
not fully discounted. And therefore, you cannot treat this mule to just
be a horse or this mule to just be a donkey. So
even Rebbi Yehuda says you can't crossbreed it with a pure with
a pure species because maybe the father does play a role or
maybe it plays a partial role. But what he does say is
you can't breed it with a another type of a mule that
has a different parentage because still the mother is the one that
clearly dominates in terms of the identity and there is a difference
and actually that then does work nicely because then what he does
wind up saying is you can't breed it with a horse, it
isn't a horse. But a mule the offspring of a horse is
very different than the mule the offspring of a donkey, which as
we've heard, one is a mule the other the hinny. So therefore
and those are different species and can't be cross-bred. So that actually
is a very logical position. Okay, that you do not consider the
father that it's irrelevant father and mother, yes maybe the father is
somewhat does play somewhat of a role, he's not completely irrelevant, but
the mother is the identity that dominates. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says שמע מינה, shma mina, so we hear from this, פשטי מספקא
ליה, pashti mesafka lei, שמע מינה, shma mina, that Rebbi Yehuda is
uncertain whether the father's role is significant at all or completely insignificant
and therefore even he agrees you cannot breed this mule with a
horse or with a donkey. Okay. So now we have the positions
that either the father is completely relevant and all mules are the
same because father and mother are equal contributors and it doesn't matter
who's contributing what, or you see that the father is irrelevant or
maybe irrelevant, and that leads to Rebbi Yehuda's position. So אמר ליה
רבי אבא לשמעיה. amar lei Rebbi Abba l'shamaya. Now Rebbi Abba says
to his servant or his assistant, his aide, אי מעיילת לי כודנייתא
בריספק, im ma'ayelas li kudnayta b'rispak,
if you're going to put for me mules in the to lead
the wagon, you're going to harness mules to lead the wagon, איין
להנך דדמיין להדדי ואייל לי. ayein l'hanech d'damyan l'hadadi v'ayeil li.
Make sure that they look similar and only then combine two mules,
because meaning make sure that they both have the same type of
voice, same type of ears, same roughly size as Mordechai was saying,
and then you'll know they'll have similar mothers. So he was concerned
with Rebbi Yehuda's position, he didn't treat all mules the same, mules
have to only mules of similar mothers are the same species, there's
a problem of having them cross
harnessed, and therefore make sure by inspecting them that you can know
that they had similar types of mothers.
What? No, no, no. On what?
No,
no. On what? Even even no. אלמא, alma, you see קסבר אין
חוששין לזרע האב. kasavar ein chosheshin l'zera ha'av. He's of the position
that you do not consider the father, and not literally completely unconcerned
because as we just said before, maybe the father plays possibly plays
a role or contributes somewhat, but the point is the father is
not considered to be equal to the mother. Right? Before we said
if the father is if you say חוששין לזרע האב, chosheshin l'zera
ha'av, it means the father is equal to the mother and therefore
all mules are the same species. So he doesn't feel that they're
equal and all mules are the same, he feels that the mother's
parentage is what most is most significant and therefore mules are of
different species based on the mother, and therefore you have to know
that if you're going to put two mules together, that they have
the same type of a mother. And what we also see is
וסימנים דאורייתא, v'simanim d'oraisa, that you can go by
character traits even to determine biblical concerns. Now this is a phrase
we actually this came up earlier in the גמרא. Gemara. This is
a phrase that originates in the world of מציאה, metzia, of lost
objects. We just had it recently in the פרשה, Parsha, right? You
take this lost object home עד דרוש אחיך אותו, ad d'rosh achicha
oso, until your brother comes and asks for it. Now how do
you know that it's actually his? Are you supposed to trust him
or not trust him? So one way you do it you say,
well give me some
identifying traits. How big was it? Where did you think you lost
it? What color was it? Etc. etc. Now there's a question
whether the ability to return a lost object based on the סימנים
simanim is whether the תורה Torah recognizes the סימנים simanim or not.
Or maybe as far as the תורה Torah is concerned you don't
trust the סימנים, simanim, maybe you're just supposed to trust everybody or
maybe there are other ways, maybe he needs to have witnesses that
can identify it and say that it was his. But we know
that at least in practice we return it based on the סימנים
simanim and a question the גמרא Gemara asks in the second פרק
Perek of בבא מציעא Bava Metzia is, is this biblical or not?
Or is it just the Rabbis that have allowed me to use
this as a basis to return it? Now when you're dealing with
monetary matters, you can say maybe it's only Rabbinic because the Rabbis
can pretty much reassign property do what they want with monetary matters.
But here it's about a prohibition, a biblical prohibition of cross-harnessing. So
from here says גמרא Gemara you see that sometimes even in biblical
matters when it's clearly a biblical concern you can make determinations of
facts based on character traits and identities and not you know without
necessarily direct knowledge. Now again of course not all issues of סימנים
simanim are the same. Right here in one case you're dealing with
trusting another person and you know and maybe also maybe you know
maybe the fact that it's was there a hundred dollars in the
wallet not a hundred dollars not all סימנים simanim are of the
same quality. The גמרא Gemara discusses סימן מובהק siman muvhak versus a
סימן שאינו מובהק. siman she'eino muvhak. Where did you lose it? In
Times Square. I know somebody that actually that actually wanted wanted an
umbrella and he didn't want to buy it so he went up
to the subway lost and found and he said did you find
an umbrella?
And they said is this it? And he said yes it is
just by the way. So not all סימנים simanim are exactly the
same. So number one you know and what סימני simanei distinguish between
one type of mule and one type of donkey mule and another
type of mule might be more reliable than trusting somebody when he's
trying to receive his אבדה aveida or what not. So it's not
necessarily all the same question. But what the גמרא Gemara does say
here is that you don't necessarily always need direct knowledge and direct
evidence to make determinations even biblical determinations and sometimes you can go
on certain signifiers and character traits and therefore he was willing here
to use that to guide him about putting the donkeys together even
though even though it could have been a biblical problem but because
it mattered who the mother was. Okay, so now we continue. תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Our rabbis taught. אותו ואת בנו Oso V'es Beno
נוהג בכלאים ובכוי. noheg b'Kila'im u'v'Koy. So אותו ואת בנו Oso V'es
Beno applies by cross-breeds. Now this is a cross-breed where the תורה
Torah explicitly says אותו ואת בנו Oso V'es Beno by a sheep
and a cow. And the גמרא Gemara understands that that's to exclude
חיה. Chaya. So actually אותו ואת בנו Oso V'es Beno does not
apply by a deer and its offspring for example. Now if you
cross-breed a sheep a sheep let's say a sheep and a goat
that would be another example although we were told that you can't
do that but I don't know if you did somehow manage to
do that the גמרא Gemara told us yesterday that אותו ואת בנו
Oso V'es Beno would apply to it because it's still within the
world of sheep and goats and cows even if it's somewhere in
in the middle of those species it's a cross-breed. So כלאים Kila'im
we said yesterday. But now we go to כוי Koy and כוי
Koy is interesting because כוי Koy is a cross-breed between a goat
and a deer. Can that be done Charlie?
I don't know but there've been very very rare cases of a
goat sheep hybrid.
Goat sheep hybrid. Okay, but the כוי Koy a כוי Koy is
some hybrid between a חיה Chaya and בהמה Behema between a goat
and a deer as we're going to see which I don't know
if we ever know that any the case ever be done anyway.
So this is now a big חידוש chiddush because this animal you
would say is part חיה Chaya and if it's part חיה Chaya
why would אותו ואת בנו Oso V'es Beno apply to it? Right
that's different than a sheep and a goat cross-breed which is all
בהמה. Behema. This is half deer half goat why would אותו ואת
בנו? Oso V'es Beno? So we are going to now say well
which is the father? Is the father the deer or is the
father I mean which is the mother right? Is the mother the
sheep or is the mother or is the mother the goat or
is the mother the deer and maybe it's really the mother that
matters and it's irrelevant who the father is. Yes.
Does a bison get classified as a חיה? Chaya?
There's actually a debate about whether a bison is a חיה Chaya
or בהמה. Behema. But there's a debate in הלכה halacha about buffalo
בופלו buphalo ב ו פ ל ו bet vav peh lamed vav
but that is European buffalo which is I believe very different than
the American bison species.
Because the American bison are cross-bred with domestic cattle.
Oh that's interesting. So if it were a חיה Chaya you would
have that case. But I think the I think the inclination is
if I remember correctly that American bison are are more definitely בהמה
Behema and that the question was more about European European buffalo. Yes.
What does a goat sheep hybrid?
In Israel you have wild goats that I don't know the name
in English but יעל Ya'el יעלים. Yaelim. That's like a חיה. Chaya.
Right. Yeah. Yeah.
So maybe and do they cross-breed you think with a
with a with deer? Do they? I don't know deer.
Oh but they are themselves a חיה. Chaya. Right. That could be.
That very well could be and right because we actually did discuss
that earlier that there are some species of wild goats that are
חיה. Chaya. So maybe they cross-breed with other goats. But the גמרא
Gemara speaks about we'll see about a cross-breeding with a צבי Tzvi
and we normally translate צבי Tzvi as deer but actually we discussed
this earlier because some say that you know that רש"י Rashi pointed
out that what the גמרא Gemara describes as the horns of the
צבי Tzvi don't really match what we have. So רש"י Rashi said
if I remember correctly that a צבי Tzvi was a what was
it? Hart. Hart. No רש"י Rashi I think said it was a
it was a a something back anyway I don't know.
Yeah eventually in Ein
Gedi where the goats would be taken to the desert yes עזי
המדבר Azei HaMidbar no the desert so the desert so. It could
happen. That goat, domesticated goat and the and the wild goat,
so
that
could be. But it partly depends on the גמרא's Gemara going to
describe a צבי, Tzevi, so partly it has to do with what
a צבי Tzevi is. So let's take a look.
Okay, so so let's take a look. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, או
תנו רבנן, O Tanu Rabbanan, נוהג בכלאים ובכוי noheig be-kilayim u-ve-koy and
with a כוי koy which is a combination of a חיה chaya
and a בהמה, behema, which is bizarre because it doesn't apply to
חיה. chaya. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, כלאים הבא מן העז
ומן הרחל, kilayim ha-ba min ha-ez u-min ha-rachel, אותו ואת בנו נוהג
בו. oto ve-et beno noheig bo. If it's a crossbreed between a
goat and a sheep, fine, and a ewe, then fine, then that
that is אותו ואת בנו oto ve-et beno because it's within the
world of בהמה. behema. כוי, Koy, however, כוי koy which is a
part חיה, chaya, אינו אותו ואת בנו נוהג בו. eino oto ve-et
beno noheig bo. It does not apply. So אמר רב חסדא, Amar
Rav Chisda, so what's this debate about? We're going to try to
tie it into our question about the role of the father. אמר
רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, איזהו כוי eizehu koy שנחלקו בו רבי
אליעזר וחכמים? she-nechelku bo Rabbi Eliezer ve-Chachamim? Which type of כוי koy
were they debating? זה הבא מן התיש ומן הצביה. zeh ha-ba min
ha-tayish u-min ha-tzviyah. From a תיש tayish is a male goat, right?
תיש, Tayish, תיש, tayish, I'm sorry, תיש tayish and צביה. tzviyah. Okay,
from a male goat and a צביה tzviyah which is maybe a
deer but that would be bizarre, so maybe it is some type
of a wild goat. Anyway, some type of a cross between a
between a חיה chaya and a בהמה, behema, but assuming that the
mother is a חיה, chaya, okay, that's צביה, tzviyah, that's going to
be critical, הילדה, ha-yaldah, and it gave birth. היכי דמי? Heichi dami?
What's the case? אילימא בתיש הבא על הצביה, Ilima be-tayish ha-ba al
ha-tzviyah, that it is the male goat that has that that that
breeds with the female צביה, tzviyah, the female חיה, chaya, וילדה, ve-yaldah,
and she gave birth, ושחט לה ולבנה, ve-shachat lah u-le-vnah, and you
slaughtered the mother and the child, so והאמר רב חסדא, ve-ha-amar Rav
Chisda, הכל מודים בצבי ובנה תיש שפטור. ha-kol modim be-tzvi u-vnah tayish
she-patur. Everybody would agree that when the mother is a חיה chaya
and the child, even if the child is like a בהמה behema
type, it looks like a goat, nevertheless you are exempt from אותו
ואת בנו. oto ve-et beno. Why? שה ובנו אמר רחמנא ולא צבי
ובנו. Seh u-vno amar Rachmana ve-lo tzvi u-vno. So what he's saying
is, look, the whole question of who the mother is only determines
the identity of the child, but the prohibition of אותו ואת בנו,
oto ve-et beno, right, you also have to know the identity of
the mother. So since the תורה Torah says אותו, oto, so since
the תורה Torah says it speaks about בהמות, behemos, if the mother
is a חיה, chaya, whatever you define the child to be, you're
not going to transgress אותו ואת בנו oto ve-et beno because you're
slaughtering a mother that is a חיה chaya and it only says
an ox or a sheep with its child. So meaning a חיה
chaya with its child—a בהמה behema with its child, this is a
חיה. chaya. So it can't be that they're debating when the mother
is this צביה, tzviyah, this deer or whatever this חיה, chaya, because
then clearly it would be excluded from the prohibition. The person's mother?
Well, then, yes, that's what we said yesterday. Okay, but it does
say the תורה Torah emphasizes a sheep or a cow, it and
its child. So and sheep and cow is understood to mean only
בהמה behema not חיה. chaya. So the key emphasis is the mother
has to be a בהמה. behema. So if the mother is a
חיה, chaya, regardless of what you consider the offspring, you're not going
to transgress. Yes. Isn't he saying yesterday the family relationship was what
matters? So it's the mother and her child, whatever species, it doesn't
matter, it's still the child of that mother, and that's their family
relationship. I understand, but that doesn't mean it's the only factor. It
means one necessary component is that they have to be considered a
family unit, which is why you might exclude father. But another factor
is that the תורה Torah speaks about בהמה behema and we understand
that it's limited to בהמה. behema. Now again, you might say well
if the reason is cruelty or whatever the reason is, why should
it be limited? Okay, I don't know the answer to that. That
goes back to Michael's point that we don't just go by whatever
we suspect the reason to be, we have to also follow the
indications in the פסוקים pesukim themselves. So we do understand that there
are two requirements: you need family unit and you need it to
be—the mother needs to be a בהמה. behema. That's not true in
this case. Let's just hold off on the questions because we don't
have much time and I want to get
a little further.
Okay, so אלא, ella, so that can't be the case because if
the mother is a חיה chaya it would not be included. אלא
בצבי הבא על התישה, Ella be-tzvi ha-ba al ha-teishah, התישה, ha-teishah, is
that right? Okay, התישה. ha-teishah. תיש, Tayish, תיישה. teishah. תיישה, Teishah, okay,
so I was right with that one. Okay, so anyway, a deer
or whatever that is that that male that mates with a female
goat, a female חיה, chaya, בהמה, behema, right. Wait, why is it
תיישה teishah and not—wait, what's the difference between a תיש tayish and
an עז? ez? No difference. Okay, fine. Okay, okay, so anyway, the
mother is the goat and therefore the mother is the בהמה.
behema. Okay, so now you have a mother who's a בהמה behema
and an offspring that's a hybrid. So maybe that's the debate: do
you consider the offspring to also be a בהמה behema or not?
So one minute, וילדה ושחט לה— ve-yaldah ve-shachat lah and then it
gave birth and you slaughtered the mother and the child.
And so one minute, how
could that be the debate?
והאמר רב חסדא, Ve'ha'amar Rav Chisda, הכל מודים בהטיא שה ובנת צבי,
hakol modim b'hitiya seh u'vnat tzvi, that if the mother was a
goat, even if the child was a deer, whatever צבי tzvi is,
but was a חיה, chaya, שחייב, she'chayav, that that does transgress. You
don't need the child to be a בהמה, behema, you only need
the mother to be a בהמה. behema. Why? שה אמר רחמנא. Seh
amar Rachmana. It says שה. seh. It says a sheep or a
cow, it and its child. So the it is the sheep or
the cow. So that has to be the בהמה. behema. But it
says and its child. It doesn't say the child has to be
a בהמה. behema. Whatever the child is. שה אמר רחמנא ובנו כל
דהו, Seh amar Rachmana u'vno kol dehu, whatever the child is, doesn't
matter. So he says, how do you have a debate about a
כוי, koy, right? Because we are going to assume that in terms
of that the mother has to be the בהמה behema and the
child doesn't matter. So regardless, so if it's a mother and the
child is a כוי, koy, you're never going to have a case
where it's a debate. If the mother's a בהמה, behema, you're always
going to be חייב. chayav. If the mother's a חיה, chaya, you're
always going to be פטור. patur. And what the identity is of
the offspring, the כוי, koy, is irrelevant to this question. Just hold
on, let's see what the answer is. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so now it's sort of like what Bobby pointed out before,
if that doesn't work in the first
generation, you go to the second generation. So the גמרא Gemara says,
one minute, לעולם בתישה בת צבי וילדה בת. Le'olam b'teisha bat tzvi
v'yalda bat. Okay, so you had a goat with a female deer,
and it gave birth to a child, that child was a כוי,
koy, was a hybrid.
ובת ילדה בן.
U'vat yalda ben. And then that כוי koy now had a child,
doesn't have to be a male child, had a child. Okay, so
now you've got the mother is a כוי koy and it has
a child. So where does it matter that something has to be
a...
we said a בהמה behema and not a חיה?
chaya? Who the mother is. So fine, we're not going to
talk about the child being a כוי, koy, that you told me
is irrelevant.
We'll talk about the mother being a כוי. koy. So you have
a mother that's a hybrid, כוי, koy, it has a child. What
is... are you חייב chayav or not? What is the identity of
a mother that's a כוי? koy? Is that כוי koy a בהמה
behema or is it a partial חיה? chaya? Okay, so let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, דכשחט לה ולברה, De'chashachat lah u'le'vrah,
so you שחט shacht this כוי koy with its offspring. Now this
כוי koy was produced by a male בהמה behema and a female...
like the female, the mother was a deer or something like that.
So if the mother was a deer, now we know that regardless
of the role of the father, this כוי koy is part חיה.
chaya. It's at least part חיה, chaya, might be full חיה, chaya,
but it's at least part חיה. chaya. So if this כוי koy
is part חיה, chaya, how could anybody say you transgress? Right? It's
part חיה. chaya. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay,
רבנן סברי, Rabbanan savri, the Rabbis hold חוששין לזרע האב, choshishin l'zera
ha'av, that we concern ourselves with the father and the father is
a בהמה. behema. So this כוי koy is part בהמה, behema, part
חיה chaya but part בהמה. behema. ושה אפילו מקצת. Ve'seh afilu miktzat.
And then they said it, this animal doesn't have to be a
full בהמה. behema. It's enough to be a part בהמה. behema. Okay,
when it says שה שור ושה seh shor v'seh etc., it means
as long as it's part בהמה, behema, that suffices. Okay, so that's
why the Rabbis say you're חייב. chayav. Why you go to the
second generation then? You can make it the same debate in the
first generation. The כוי koy itself, right? They are debating, but it
matters what the mother is, not the child. So we had to
have... so that's why. I thought our case was that this כוי
koy now has an offspring. It does, because you have to שחט
shacht the mother and the child. Okay. ורבי אליעזר סבר, V'Rabbi Eliezer
savar, we're not talking about the second generation, we're talking about the
first generation כוי, koy, but it's שחט shachted with its child, whatever
that child is. ורבי אליעזר סבר אין חוששין לזרע האב, V'Rabbi Eliezer
savar ein choshishin l'zera ha'av, the father's contribution is irrelevant. Okay, ושה
אפילו מקצת לא אמרינן, Ve'seh afilu miktzat lo amrinan, and I don't
care that you only need it to be part בהמה. behema. This
is zero בהמה. behema. This is no בהמה. behema. So, just to
sum this up, okay, basically we're saying when אותו ואת בנו oto
v'et bno applies only to בהמה, behema, that does not mean the
child of the... בנו bno is irrelevant, בהמה חיה, behema chaya, the
mother has to be בהמה. behema. And what if the mother is
a crossbreed of a בהמה behema and a חיה, chaya, this כוי?
koy? So now we're going to say that the assumption is as
long as it's part בהמה, behema, that's enough. It doesn't have to
be full בהמה behema as long as it's part בהמה. behema. So,
so if the mother is a חיה chaya and the father is
a בהמה, behema, is it part בהמה? behema? So one opinion says
yes, the father's contribution matters, חוששין לזרע האב. choshishin l'zera ha'av. So
at least it's part בהמה behema and therefore it's in the category.
And the other says the father's contribution is irrelevant and therefore it's
100% חיה chaya and therefore you do not transgress. Is this all
the same debate, the חכמים Chachamim and חנניה? Chananya? חנניה? Chananya? Yeah,
yeah, except that here the one that says you reject the father
says you completely reject the father. I remember before we said he
was מספקא ליה *mesafke lei*, here we're saying you completely reject the
father. Okay, so let's get a little further. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
וליפלוג *uliflog* as Micah was implicitly saying בחושש לזרע אב *bechoshesh lezera
av* בפלוגתא דחנניא ורבנן *beplugta dechananya verabbanan*. So if all they're debating
is do you care about the father or not, why are they
debating about a כוי *koy*? Why don't they argue about what we
started with, whether you're חייב *chayav* for שחט *shechting* the father and
the child, which the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes is the more straightforward
way of asking whether the father matters? So the גמרא *Gemara* says
אי פליגי בההיא *ei peligi behee*, if they had debated just the
question of whether אותו ואת בנו *oto ve'et beno* includes the father
and the child, הוה אמינא *hava amina*, I would have thought בהא
אפילו רבנן מודה *beha afilu rabbanan modeh* דסבירא ליה אפילו מקצת צד
לא אמרינן *desavre lei afilu miktzat tzad lo amrinan*. I would have
said look, I could say the father plays a role and I
could say that you transgress for father and child, but when you
say you're חייב *chayav* for a כוי *koy*, you have to say
more than the father plays a role. You have to say that
even though this כוי *koy* is only part בהמה *behema*, that's enough
to transgress, right? So that's what the גמרא *Gemara* is saying is
it's not enough to tell me we care about the father. Yes,
you could if the רבנן *Rabbanan* just told me we care about
the father and you're חייב *chayav* for the father and the child,
I would have known we care about the father, but I would
not have known that if the animal is only part בהמה *behema*,
that's enough to be חייב *chayav* for it. And therefore they had
to tell me this other debate, that if you have a כוי
*koy* whose father is a בהמה *behema*, you're still חייב *chayav*, it's
enough to just be part בהמה *behema*, that is also sufficient. Okay,
now we're going to just try to work out a few more
points about this. We care according to the רבנן *Rabbanan*, we care
about the father, and that means number one, that you're חייב *chayav*
for שחט *shechting* the father and the child, and then we go
further to say not only do we care about the father, but
if an animal is even a part בהמה *behema*, it's enough to
be חייב *chayav* for it. So a כוי *koy* whose father is
a בהמה *behema*, although it's only part בהמה *behema*, it's enough to
be חייב *chayav* when you שחט *shecht* the כוי *koy* and the
child. Okay, so two positions. Alright. תנן *Tenan*, now let's ask another
question. כוי *Koy* אין שוחטין אותו ביום טוב *ein shochtin oto beyom
tov*. You can't שחט *shecht* it on יום טוב *Yom Tov* because
you don't know if it's a חיה *chaya* or a בהמה *behema*.
And if it's a חיה *chaya*, you can שחט *shecht* it on
יום טוב *Yom Tov* and you cover the blood. And if it's
a בהמה *behema*, you שחט *shecht* it on יום טוב *Yom Tov*
and you don't cover the blood. But if you don't know whether
it's a חיה *chaya* or a בהמה *behema*, then you can't שחט
*shecht* it on יום טוב *Yom Tov* because if maybe you don't
need to cover the blood and you'll cover the blood and have
done an unnecessary מלאכה *melacha* on יום טוב *Yom Tov*. Alright, I'm
not going to get into it, whether it's דאורייתא *de'oraita* or דרבנן
*derabbanan*, but whatever, we don't want you covering blood if you don't
have to. Okay, so כוי *koy*, since you don't know if you
have to, you're stuck, you have to play it safe, but you
can't do it because it's יום טוב *Yom Tov*. So don't שחט
*shecht* it on יום טוב *Yom Tov*. ואם שחטו *Ve'im shechato*, if
you did שחט *shecht* it, אין מכסין את דמו *ein mechasin et
damo*. Better, you know, a sin of omission than a sin of
commission. So don't do anything, don't cover the blood, you'll cover it
after יום טוב *Yom Tov*. Okay, so now we see that this
כוי *koy* has a status of a ספק safek, *safek*. Okay, whether
it's a חיה *chaya* and whether you cover the blood. So במה
עסקינן *bameh askinan*? What type of a כוי *koy* are we talking
about? אילימא בתייא שבא על צביה *Ilima betaya sheba al tzeviya*, if
it's that the mother was a חיה *chaya* and the father was
a goat, וילדה *veyaleda* and has child, בין רבנן בין רבי אליעזר
*bein Rabbanan bein Rabbi Eliezer*, לשחוט ולכסות *lishchot ulechassot*. Since the mother
is a חיה *chaya*, it at least is part חיה *chaya*, and
if it's part חיה *chaya*, we're assuming that part suffices. And therefore
you should definitely have to cover the blood. So what type of
a כוי *koy* do we have a doubt about? If it's a
כוי *koy* whose mother's a חיה *chaya*, so everybody agrees that it's
at least part חיה *chaya*, and therefore you should have to cover
the blood. חיה ואפילו מקצת חיה *chaya va'afilu miktzat chaya*, even if
it's only part חיה *chaya*. אלא בצבי הבא על התייא *Ela betzvi
haba al hataya*. It must be that the mother was the בהמה
*behema* and the question is does the father's part חיה *chaya* matter?
וילדה *Veyaleda* and gave birth. אי לרבנן *Ei lerabbanan*, if it's the
רבנן *Rabbanan*, לשחוט ולכסות *lishchot ulechassot*, so שחט *shecht* and cover because
the father does matter. אי לרבי אליעזר *Ei leRabbi Eliezer*, and if
it's according to רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*, לשחוט ולא לכסות *lishchot velo
lechassot*. Don't cover because we don't care about the father. We don't
still know where's a case where it's a ספק safek *safek*. If
the father's a חיה *chaya*, so according to the רבנן *Rabbanan* that
matters, cover, and according to רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* it doesn't matter,
don't cover. So the גמרא *Gemara* says לעולם בצבי הבא על התייא
*le'olam betzvi haba al hataya*. The mother is a בהמה *behema*, the
father is a חיה *chaya*. לרבנן *Lerabbanan*, and the רבנן *Rabbanan*, going
back to what we said before, who say that you go by
the father, באמת ספוקי מספקא להו *be'emet sefuki mesafke lehu*, they are
uncertain. אי חוששין לזרע האב chosheshin lezera ha'av או אין חוששין *ei
chosheshin lezera ha'av o ein chosheshin*. Do we really go by the
father or not? So they don't know whether to consider the father.
Okay, and we will end here, we'll pick up with this tomorrow.
But basically we're saying the רבנן *Rabbanan* say you might go by
the father, so this כוי *koy* might be a חיה *chaya*, but
you don't know for sure, so you're stuck, you don't know to
cover the blood. But because also it might go by the father,
when it comes to the issue of אותו ואת בנו *oto ve'et
beno*, you have to say don't שחט *shecht* it. This thing that's
a part בהמה *behema* might be a part בהמה *behema* with its
child because it might be a part בהמה *behema* and therefore it
might be prohibited. So we are now saying that you know, if
you have a doubt whether you go by the father, you'll have
to play it safe. So we think the ספק safek. is that
maybe we go by the father as a possibility, we don't know
for sure. Well, let's think about it. If it was a ודאי,
vadai, you'd go by the father in everything, right? If it's a
ספק, safek it's really the same thing, except that we don't know
for sure, so we have to go by the father in all
situations where it could result in an איסור. issur. But we wouldn't
use that to create a היתר. heter. This is the standard rule
of ספיקא דאורייתא לחומרא. safeka de'oraita lechumra. So why does the גמרא
have to say that if you have a ספק safek you follow
the father? The גמרא is saying that the question of whether we
say חוששין לזרע האב is itself the ספק. If we say we
do follow the father, then it becomes a ספק and we have
to be מחמיר. machmir. If we were sure we don't follow the
father, there'd be no ספק at all. So the חומרא chumra comes
from the fact that we might follow the father.